# Ismail Ali

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

#### Links

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ismailyma/

#### **Skills**

HTML

CSS

JavaScri<u>pt</u>

Node.js

React.js

JSX

Express.js

Next.js

PostgreSQL

TDD

Git & GitHub

Heroku

Netlify

Vercel

**JIRA** 

Confluence

Pair & Mob programming

Remote working

Agile and Scrum

Full UK Driving Licence

#### **Hobbies**

Travelling
Reading
Listening to podcasts
Collecting & restoring trainers
Football
Fitness
Hiking

## Languages

English

Somali

Arabic

Danish

### **Profile**

I'm a full-stack software developer with experience in working collaboratively and creatively to solve real-world problems within remote, cross-functional, technical, and agile teams. A keen curiosity in maths, physics, and problem-solving bore a real passion for the world of innovation within me. This propelled me to embark on a role in tech especially given the added flexibility of being able to use my skills to exercise my entrepreneurial spirit and bring about real impact and change through tech. My interests lie in the front-end of software engineering as well as UX/UI design, however, I'm keen to explore full-stack roles first. I'm incredibly excited to be part of this industry and continue my journey of life-long learning.

# **Courses**

### School of Code, Birmingham

SEPTEMBER 2020 - JANUARY 2021

During my time at the boot-camp, I learnt how to become a collaborative, creative problem solver and a full-stack developer. I was tasked with two projects where I collaborated within agile teams where we implemented agile principles throughout the SDLC. We did this by working in short iterative sprints, completing daily tickets and delivering working software every few days. We created user personas and stories, wire-framing, story-pointing, pre-mortems, daily stand-ups, pair/mob-programming, sprint reviews and retrospectives. We also used various software tools for project management such as GitHub, Trello, Jira and Confluence.

# **Projects**

# Software Developer, MENTORMATCH (Mid-term Project), Birmingham

As a team we developed an app that enhances the mentor and mentee experience at the School of Code. We solved this problem by creating a single platform where mentors sign up and mentees are able to view profiles of all the mentors and select the one they feel best caters to their professional development needs. We balanced the stack and I was able to work on both the front-end and back-end through pair programming; I took part in building the back-end server and database using expressJS, nodeJS, postgreSQL and Heroku. I also utilised my skills to engineer the front-end using reactJS, HTML5 and CSS3. After one week we finally presented our MVP to a panel of four CTOs and CEOs.

# Software Developer, Progress Plus (Final Project), Birmingham

We engineered an app called Progress Plus that's been designed for the School of Code as a centralised hub where bootcampers can track their progress on the course and overcome 'imposter syndrome'. We deployed our front-end using Vercel initially as HTTPS, CI/CD and connection to a custom domain was very quick and enabled us to test user engagement immediately and make informed decisions upon each iteration. Conducting this project fully remotely meant we particularly sharpened our communication and project management skills as well as working within the agile framework. We used Figma for prototyping and wire-framing. For the front-end development we used NextJS, Semantic UI and CSS. My main focus initially was on implementing a UX/UI design for a lightweight user experience. After completing our MVP, we deployed using AWS ECR and AWS ECS buckets. Our database was set up on Cloud Atlas the mongoDB database as a service which afforded our data some flexibility. We pair-programmed and rotated roles and after setting up the back-end I transitioned to developing the front-end using React. We presented this project after 4 weeks to a panel of over a hundred industry experts, tech professionals and startup founders and entrepreneurs who gave us fantastic feedback.

# **Employment History**

# Warehouse Operative, Hello Fresh, Banbury

AUGUST 2020 - PRESENT

Manage time to reach the daily target of picking and sending off stock, ensure maintenance of health and safety whilst using Forklifts and Lollops.

#### Warehouse Operative, Royal Mail, Nuneaton

JUNE 2020 - AUGUST 2020

Manage time to reach the daily target of picking and sorting mail, ensure maintenance of health and safety and to manage delivered goods.

### Sales Assistant, JD, Birmingham

APRIL 2018 - MARCH 2020

Responsibility to ensure customers are served to the highest levels of satisfaction, exercise leadership when training new staff/managing current inexperienced staff, manage time in stockroom picking trainers for multiple customers, supervise the doors to keep theft to a minimum and confront shoplifters.

## **Education**

# BTEC, Joseph Chamberlaine College, Birmingham

SEPTEMBER 2017 - JUNE 2019

Level 3 BTEC Applied Science Extended Diploma (Distinction, Distinction, Merit)

### GCSE, Rockwood Academy, Birmingham

SEPTEMBER 2012 - JULY 2017

8 GCSE's A\*-C

# **Extra-curricular activities**

### Volunteer, African Relief Fund, Birmingham

JULY 2016 - PRESENT

#### Main Duties:

- Working behind computers
- Fundraising on the streets of Birmingham
- Responsibly counting money raised
- Recording statistics on spreadsheets
- Updating statistics on computer
- Suggesting new ideas for events.

# References

## Chris Meah from School of Code

chris@schoolofcode.co.uk